

RESEARCHER IN ASTRONOMICAL INSTRUMENTATION | AUSTRALIAN NATIONAL UNIVERSITY

Research School of Astronomy & Astrophysics, Mount Stromlo Observatory, Cotter Road, Weston Creek ACT 2611, AUSTRALIA

□ (+61) 459 942 663 | Mansen.jonah833@gmail.com | Majonahhansen.github.io | Imajonahthansen

Summary.

Current researcher in astronomical instrumentation at the Australian National University; soon to join ETH Zurich. Career aim is to work as a researcher in a field related to astronomy, satellites, and astronomical instrumentation. Particularly interested in optical/IR space interferometry, with involvement in the Large Interferometer For Exoplanets (LIFE) mission concept.

Education

Australian National University

Canberra, ACT

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY

Feb. 2020 - Oct. 2023

- Recipient of an RTP and Dean's Merit HDR Supplimentary Scholarship in Science
- Supervised by Prof. Michael Ireland, Dr. Tony Travouillon, Dr Tiphaine Lagadec and Prof. John Monnier

Australian National University

Canberra, ACT

BACHELOR OF PHILOSOPHY - SCIENCE, HONOURS IN ASTRONOMY AND ASTROPHYSICS

Feb. 2016 - Dec. 2019

- Recipient of a Tuckwell Scholarship
- High Distinction Average and University Medal recipient

Employment History

Australian National University

Canberra, ACT

STUDENT RESEARCHER

Jul. 2016 - Present

- PhD project centred on developing a beam combiner for the Pyxis interferometer (see www.mso.anu.edu.au/pyxis for more information). Have also been involved with the LIFE (Large Interferometer For Exoplanets) initiative (see www.life-space-mission.com) in simulating nulling interferometry compatible telescope configurations. Interested in the properties of Mira variables using high angular resolution measurements from the CHARA and VLTI interferometric facilities.
- Honours project with Prof. Michael Ireland in simulating a linear formation flying, space interferometer mission with the aim of detecting biosignatures on exoplanets.
- Undergraduate projects with Prof. Michael Ireland, Dr Brad Tucker, Dr Tony Travouillon and Dr Luca Casagrande. These varied from tracing back the positions of stars in order to determine cluster membership, to building an instrument designed to measure turbulence inside a telescope dome, to identifying relationships between exoplanets and their host star's properties.

Mount Stromlo Observatory

Canberra, ACT

OUTREACH ASSISTANT

Apr. 2018 - Oct. 2023

- Assisted with the ANU Stargazing World Record Attempt.
- Regularly give tours and present to school and private groups at Mt Stromlo Observatory.
- Assisted in giving talks to schools around regional South Australia and local Canberran schools.
- Given many talks and written newspaper articles about astronomy (see http://www.mso.anu.edu.au/~jhansen/ #outreach)

HEO Robotics Sydney, NSW

PHD INTERN

Oct. 2020 - Jan. 2021

- $\bullet \ \ \text{Researched and designed an optical payload for a future space situational awareness (SSA) satellite.}$
- Purchased and tested a potential optical system, both for optical quality and for survivability in space.

Australian Astronomical Observatory

Sydney, NSW

STUDENT FELLOWSHIP HOLDER

Dec. 2017 - Feb. 2018

- Conducted a research project with Dr. Barnaby Norris in Adaptive Optics Instrumentation.
- Designed and tested a photonic lantern based wavefront sensor, designed to increase the speed and accuracy at which atmospheric turbulence can be detected.

Australian National University

STUDENT AMBASSADOR Jan. 2017 - Jan. 2020

- Lead tours of the ANU campus on a fortnightly basis.
- Team leader for major events, such as ANU Commencement Address and ANU Open Day.
- Gave presentations to prospective ANU students.

Max Planck Institute for Astronomy

Heidelberg, Germany

Canberra, ACT

STUDENT RESEARCHER

Jul. - Aug. 2015

• Conducted a research project into galaxy evolution and morphology with Dr Kai Noeske.

Honours & Awards

AWARDS

2020	-2023	B Dean's Merit HDR Supplimentary Scholarship in Science, Australian National University	Canberra, ACT	
20)22	Joan Duffield Research Award Scholarship, Australian National University	Canberra, ACT	
20)20	Peter McGregor Scholarship, Australian National University	Canberra, ACT	
20)19	University Medal, Australian National University	Canberra, ACT	
2016	- 201	9 Tuckwell Scholarship , Australian National University	Canberra, ACT	
2016, 20	, 2017)19	Chancellor's Letter of Commendation , Australian National University	Canberra, ACT	
2017, 2018 Brescia Award for Academic Achievement , Ursula Hall, Australian National University Canberra, ACT				
20)15	Governor's Commendation Award for Outstanding Achievement, South Australian Certificate of Education Merit Ceremony	Adelaide, SA	
20)15	Chinner Memorial Prize (Valedictorian Award), Loxton High School	Loxton, SA	
Opportunities				
20)15	Participant, International Summer Science School	Heidelberg, Germany	
20)15	Participant, National Youth Science Forum	Canberra, ACT	

Publications_

Hansen, Jonah T., Samuel Wade, Michael J. Ireland, Tony D. Travouillon, Tiphaine Lagadec, Nicholas Herrald, Joice Mathew, Stephanie Monty, and Adam D. Rains (Oct. 2023). "Pyxis: A ground-based demonstrator for formation-flying optical interferometry". In: *Journal of Astronomical Telescopes, Instruments, and Systems* 9, 045001, p. 045001. DOI: 10.1117/1.JATIS. 9.4.045001. arXiv: 2307.07211 [astro-ph.IM].

Hansen, Jonah T., Michael J. Ireland, Romain Laugier, and LIFE Collaboration (Feb. 2023). "Large Interferometer For Exoplanets (LIFE). VII. Practical implementation of a five-telescope kernel-nulling beam combiner with a discussion on instrumental uncertainties and redundancy benefits". In: *Astronomy and Astrophysics* 670, A57, A57. DOI: 10.1051/0004-6361/202243863. arXiv: 2204.12291 [astro-ph.IM].

Munro, Josephine, **Jonah Hansen**, Tony Travouillon, Doris Grosse, and Andrei Tokovinin (Jan. 2023). "Dome seeing analysis of the Anglo-Australian Telescope". In: *Journal of Astronomical Telescopes, Instruments, and Systems* 9, 017004, p. 017004. DOI: 10.1117/1.JATIS.9.1.017004.

Hansen, Jonah T., Michael J. Ireland, and the LIFE Collaboration (Aug. 2022). "Large Interferometer For Exoplanets (LIFE). IV. Ideal kernel-nulling array architectures for a space-based mid-infrared nulling interferometer". In: *Astronomy and Astrophysics* 664, A52, A52. DOI: 10.1051/0004-6361/202243107. arXiv: 2201.04891 [astro-ph.IM].

Hansen, Jonah T., Michael J. Ireland, Tony Travouillon, Samuel Wade, Michael Ellis, Steven Ellis, Shanae King, Tiphaine Lagadec, Joice Mathew, Patrick Miller, Stephanie Monty, Adam Rains, Thomas Scott, and Hancheng Shao (Aug. 2022). "The Pyxis Interferometer (I): scientific context, metrology system, and optical design". In: Optical and Infrared Interferometry and Imaging VIII. Ed. by Antoine Mérand, Stephanie Sallum, and Joel Sanchez-Bermudez. Vol. 12183. Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE) Conference Series, 121831B, 121831B. DOI: 10.1117/12.2627768.

Munro, Josephine, **Jonah Hansen**, Doris Grosse, Tony Travouillon, and Andrei Tokovinin (Aug. 2022). "Results of the dome turbulence sensor at the Anglo-Australian Telescope". In: *Observatory Operations: Strategies, Processes, and Systems IX*. Ed. by David S. Adler, Robert L. Seaman, and Chris R. Benn. Vol. 12186. Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE) Conference Series, 121860A, 121860A. DOI: 10.1117/12.2629702.

- Wade, Samuel, **Jonah T. Hansen**, Michael J. Ireland, Tony Travouillon, Nicholas Bohlsen, Logan Corry, Steven Ellis, Nicholas Herrald, Weihao Luo, Stephen Madden, Joseph Mangos, Michael Polkinghorne, and Kunlun Yan (Aug. 2022). "The Pyxis Interferometer (II): control system, telescope, and mechanical design". In: *Optical and Infrared Interferometry and Imaging VIII*. Ed. by Antoine Mérand, Stephanie Sallum, and Joel Sanchez-Bermudez. Vol. 12183. Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE) Conference Series, 121831C, p. 121831C. DOI: 10.1117/12.2627772.
- Hansen, Jonah T., Michael J. Ireland, Andrew Ross-Adams, Simon Gross, Tiphaine Lagadec, Tony Travouillon, and Joice Mathew (Apr. 2022). "Interferometric beam combination with a triangular tricoupler photonic chip". In: *Journal of Astronomical Telescopes, Instruments, and Systems* 8, 025002, p. 025002. DOI: 10.1117/1.JATIS.8.2.025002. arXiv: 2112.05017 [astro-ph.IM].
- **Hansen, Jonah T.**, Luca Casagrande, Michael J. Ireland, and Jane Lin (Mar. 2021). "Confirming known planetary trends using a photometrically selected Kepler sample". In: *Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society* 501.4, pp. 5309–5318. DOI: 10.1093/mnras/staa3921. arXiv: 2009.08154 [astro-ph.EP].
- **Hansen, Jonah T.**, Michael J. Ireland, Tony Travouillon, Tiphaine Lagadec, Joice Mathew, and Nicholas Herrald (Dec. 2020). "Linear formation-flying astronomical interferometry in low-Earth orbit: a feasibility study". In: *Space Telescopes and Instrumentation 2020: Optical, Infrared, and Millimeter Wave*. Ed. by Makenzie Lystrup, Marshall D. Perrin, Natalie Batalha, Nicholas Siegler, and Edward C. Tong. Vol. 11443. International Society for Optics and Photonics. SPIE, pp. 955–967. DOI: 10.1117/12.2560890.
- Lagadec, T., M. Ireland, **J. Hansen**, J. Mathew, T. Travouillon, and S. Madden (Dec. 2020). "Compact unambiguous differential path-length metrology with dispersed Fabry-Perot laser diodes for a space interferometer array". In: *Optical and Infrared Interferometry and Imaging VII*. Ed. by Peter G. Tuthill, Antoine Mérand, and Stephanie Sallum. Vol. 11446. International Society for Optics and Photonics. SPIE, pp. 549–556. DOI: 10.1117/12.2561927.
- **Hansen, Jonah T.** and Michael J. Ireland (May 2020). "A linear formation-flying astronomical interferometer in low Earth orbit". In: *Publications of the Astronomical Society of Australia* 37, e019, e019. DOI: 10.1017/pasa.2020.13. arXiv: 1912. 02350 [astro-ph.IM].
- Crundall, Timothy D., Michael J. Ireland, Mark R. Krumholz, Christoph Federrath, Maruša Žerjal, and **Jonah T. Hansen** (Nov. 2019). "Chronostar: a novel Bayesian method for kinematic age determination I. Derivation and application to the β Pictoris moving group". In: *Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society* 489.3, pp. 3625–3642. DOI: 10.1093/mnras/stz2376. arXiv: 1902.07732 [astro-ph.SR].

Service Roles and Leadership _____

2022-2023 Outreach Team Leader, Mt Stromlo Outreach Program	Canberra, ACT
2022-2023 HDR Student Representative , Research School of Astronomy and Astrophysics Executive	Canberra, ACT
2021-2023 Meeting Coordinator, Planets Group Meeting, Instrumentation Journal Club	Canberra, ACT
Member, Research School of Astronomy and Astrophysics Telescope Time Allocation Committee	Canberra, ACT
2020, 2021 Organiser and Advisor , Mt Stromlo Student Seminars	Canberra, ACT
2016-2019 Volunteer and Group Leader, ConocoPhillips Science Experience	Canberra, ACT
2017-2018 Secretary and Treasurer , ANU Physics Society	Canberra, ACT
2018 Organiser , ANU National Science Week Program	Canberra, ACT

Presentations

9th Australian Exoplanet Workshop 2023

PRESENTER ON THE PYXIS INTERFEROMETER

Astronomical Society of Australia, Annual Science Meeting 2023

PRESENTER ON THE PYXIS INTERFEROMETER

Keck Institute For Space Studies Workshop: Exploring Exoplanets With Interferometry

PRESENTER ON THE PYXIS INTERFEROMETER AND ARCHITECTURES FOR THE LARGE INTERFEROMETER FOR EXOPLANETS

20th Australian Space Research Conference

PRESENTER ON THE PYXIS INTERFEROMETER

Sydney, Australia

Sep. 2023

Sydney, Australia

Jul. 2023

Pasadena, California, USA

Nov. 2022

Sydney, Australia

Sep. 2022

Optical and Infrared Interferometry and Imaging VIII, SPIE Astronomical Telescopes and Instrumentation

PRESENTER ON THE PYXIS INTERFEROMETER (PAPERS 12183-48 AND 12183-49)

Montreal, Canada

Jul. 2022

Astronomical Society of Australia, Annual Science Meeting 2022

POSTER PRESENTER ON THE PYXIS INTERFEROMETER

Hybrid; Melbourne, Australia

Jun. 2022

Astronomical Society of Australia, Annual Science Meeting 2021

POSTER PRESENTER ON THE PYXIS INTERFEROMETER

Hybrid; Hobart, Australia

Jul. 2021

43rd COSPAR Scientific Assembly

PRESENTER ON FORMATION-FLYING INTERFEROMETRY IN LOW EARTH ORBIT (PAPER E1.20-0013-21)

Online; Sydney, Australia Jan. 2021

Space Telescopes and Instrumentation 2020: Optical, Infrared, and Millimeter Wave, SPIE Astronomical Telescopes and Instrumentation

Online

POSTER PRESENTER ON FORMATION-FLYING INTERFEROMETRY IN LOW EARTH ORBIT (PAPER 11443-177)

Dec. 2020